{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This program was aided by the studies of research teams under Bill Moyers and Richard Goodwin. This program was first described in a speech at Ohio University, where it was claimed that “no child will go unfed, and no youngster will go unschooled.” Poll taxes were outlawed under this program’s Voting Rights Act. Medicaid and Medicare were established under, for ten points, what set of domestic welfare programs under Lyndon B. Johnson?",
      "answer": "Great Society"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event produced a list of banned books known as the Index Librorum Prohibitorum and defined the Canon of the Bible to include the whole of the Vulgate and exclude Third and Fourth Maccabees. The papal bull Benedictus Deus upheld the doctrines produced by this meeting, which was presided over by both Julius III and Pius IV. This meeting set the number of sacraments at 7 and condemned the 95 Theses of Martin Luther. For ten points, name this 16th century church council that denounced the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": "Council of Trent"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. Planners decided to use this type of construction for Kansai International Airport to avoid noise complaints and the hassles of eminent domain. The Palm Jumeirah is this type of construction in the Persian Gulf, found near similar constructions in the shape of the countries of the world on the Dubai coastline. The Chinese “Great Wall of Sand” plans to use, for ten points, what process to build additional ports and runways in the South China Sea?",
      "answer": "artificial islands"
    },
    {
      "question": "This war escalated when the desecration of the Hiera Orgas led to the passing of the harsh Megarian Decree. The Thirty Years’ Peace failed to create a lasting end to this war. One side in this war aimed to use the port of Piraeus to supply itself while defending from within the Long Walls, but that strategy was thwarted after it lost at Aegospotami. Plague took the life of Pericles during, for ten points, what 5th century BC war between Athens and Sparta?",
      "answer": "Peloponnesian War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting of this man also depicts Simon Fraser and many other people who weren’t actually present at the historical event in question. In that painting, a Native American resting his head on his chin views this man in a position similar to that of Christ after the Crucifixion. This man wears a red army coat and is being attended by a kneeling doctor in a blue coat. A Benjamin West painting depicts, for ten points, what British general who died at the 1759 Battle of Quebec?",
      "answer": [
        "James Wolfe",
        "The Death of General Wolfe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire built sculptures of winged lions with human heads that were known as lamassu. Artifacts of this empire were excavated at Dur-Sharrukin, a former capital located in present-day Khorsabad. This empire besieged Hezekiah at Jerusalem during the reign of Sennacherib. A large ancient library was built by this empire’s ruler Ashurbanipal. For ten points, name this Iron Age empire centered at Nineveh.",
      "answer": "Neo-Assyrian Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s son founded the first settlement by Spain in Uruguay while exploring the Rio de la Plata. The John Day letter recorded this man’s voyages, which were commemorated by a tower in Bristol, England. This man commanded the Matthew to Cape Bonavista. The Vikings had previously reached the land that this man explored, which lies near Cape Breton Island in Nova Scotia. For ten points, name this Genoan sailor who sailed for Henry VII to explore Canada for England.",
      "answer": "John Cabot or Giovanni Caboto"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these devices was co-developed by the developer of the Heimlich maneuver and the original voice actor of Tigger. At Wayne State University, one of these devices was used in a surgery on Henry Opitek after he was found to be suffering shortness of breath. The first of these devices was invented by Vladimir Demikhov while experimenting on dogs. One of these devices designed by Robert Jarvik has tubing made of polyurethane and contains pneumatically-fuelled ventricles. For ten points, name this medical device, a manmade version of a critical organ.",
      "answer": "artificial hearts"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was preceded by George Crook’s withdrawal thanks to losses at Rosebud. Frederick Benteen arrived in time to save Marcus Reno’s detachment during this battle, whose losing commander was knocked off his horse by Buffalo Calf Road Woman while his men were surrounded on a hilltop. The 7th Cavalry was annihilated in, for ten points, what 1876 victory for Sitting Bull and Crazy Horse?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Little Bighorn",
        "Custer’s Last Stand",
        "Battle of the Greasy Grass"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician sent Robert Napier to rescue missionaries from Tewodros II in the punitive expedition to Abyssinia. Lionel de Rothschild loaned this man money to finance the purchase of the Suez Canal. This man authorized the Royal Titles act to name Queen Victoria as Empress of India and served as the only Jewish prime minister to date. For ten points, name this Conservative prime minister who rivaled William Gladstone in 19th century England.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Near the end of this opera, the title character questions “How much of what we did was good?” while pondering his old age. Within this opera, the whipping of a woman during a performance of The Red Detachment of Women shocks one character into rushing the stage to help; in response, another character sings the aria “I am the wife of Mao Tse-Tung.” For ten points, name this John Adams opera that depicts a landmark 1972 presidential visit to China.",
        "answer": "Nixon in China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This politician has the lowest singing role in Nixon in China. During The Red Detachment of Women, the actor playing this politician re-appears as the cruel man ordering the whipping.",
        "answer": "Henry Kissinger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began after one side marched through Normandy to provoke the Duke of Guyenne. A successful attack against the enemy baggage train in this battle was the only bright spot for the losing side, whose heavy cavalry was neutralized by heavy rains, mounted stakes, and English longbows. For ten points, name this 1415 battle, a victory for England in the Hundred Years’ War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Agincourt was fought on October 25th, a feast day named in honor of this martyred Christian saint.",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Crispin",
          "Saint Crispin’s Day"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Barnard collected a set of 61 prints in his Photographic Views of this campaign. A telegram in which a president said “go as you propose” gave its leader permission to carry out this campaign, during which Orlando Poe was tasked with dismantling bridges. Special Field Orders Number 15 was issued after this campaign concluded with the capture of thousands of bales of cotton and a crucial port city. An estimated $100 million dollars in damage was caused by, for ten points, what campaign through Georgia led by William Tecumseh Sherman?",
        "answer": [
          "Sherman’s March to the Sea",
          "Savannah Campaign"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the March to the Sea, Sherman ordered scorched earth tactics like foraging, as well as destroying these specific items, which then became known as “Sherman’s neckties.”",
        "answer": "rails"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ingvar Kamprad, the founder of IKEA, drew controversy by moving his production facilities to this country. This country liberalized under the leadership of Wladyslaw Gomulka [vlad-ee-slav go-moo-ka]. The wave of protests that eventually overthrew this country’s Communist government began at the Lenin Shipyard. For ten points, name this Eastern European country where Lech Walesa [lek vah-wen-sah] led the Solidarity movement.",
        "answer": "Poland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lenin Shipyard is found in, and now named for, this Polish city on the coast of the Baltic Sea.",
        "answer": "Gdansk or Danzig"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A particularly hazardous season in this region in 1988 is sometimes referred to as the “Summer of Fire.” The establishment of the Lamar Buffalo Ranch in this region helped boost its population of bison. The “capture and destruction [of wildlife] for the purposes of merchandise or profit” were banned in an 1872 act that made this region the first of its type. For ten points, name this national park containing Old Faithful, the first national park in the US.",
        "answer": "Yellowstone National Park"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of Yellowstone’s roads, trails, and facilities were built or repaired by workers with this New Deal agency, which employed young men in manual labor on governmental land to maintain America’s natural resources.",
        "answer": "Civilian Conservation Corps or CCC"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader embarked on a political purge in a “Corrective Revolution,” and he liberalized his country’s economy through his policy of intifah. With Hafez al-Assad, this leader launched Operation Badr against a neighboring country. This politician was assassinated in 1981 by radical forces inside his country, largely because he had signed the Camp David Accords three years earlier. For ten points, name this man who succeeded Gamal Abdel Nasser as President of Egypt.",
        "answer": "Muhammad Anwar el-Sadat"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anwar Sadat shared the Nobel Peace Prize for signing the Camp David Accords with this prime minister of Israel, who later invaded Lebanon in 1982 in an attempt to combat the PLO.",
        "answer": "Menachem Begin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the beginning of this event, a cannon firing led to the release of 25,000 pigeons, many of whom defecated on the audience. Avery Brundage controversially pulled Marty Glickman and Sam Stoller out of participation in this event, where Louis Zamperini competed in the 5,000 meters and Luz Long competed against an African-American track and field star who won four gold medals. For ten points, name these pre-World War II Olympic games that were overseen by Adolf Hitler.",
        "answer": [
          "1936 Summer Olympics in Berlin",
          "any answer with Olympics and at least two of the other three underlined parts."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This German filmmaker and Nazi propagandist documented the 1936 Summer Olympics in her 1938 film Olympia.",
        "answer": "Leni Riefenstahl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who was the first to reprint a Masonic book in America, compiled thirteen virtues in his unfinished autobiography. This ambassador to France obtained the letters of Thomas Hutchinson, and drew a political cartoon of a chopped-up snake with the words “Join or Die” to support his Albany Plan. For ten points, name this Founding Father and author of Poor Richard’s Almanack, who performed a famous kite experiment in a thunderstorm.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As a teenager, Franklin wrote letters to his brother’s newspaper, the New-England Courant, under this pen name.",
        "answer": "Mrs. Silence Dogood"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Colonial Virginia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Pre-1699 capital of Virginia, the first permanent English settlement in the Americas.",
          "answer": "Jamestown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crop that was introduced to Virginia by John Rolfe and popularized in England by Sir Walter Raleigh.",
          "answer": "tobacco"
        },
        {
          "question": "First representative assembly in America, formed in 1642 in Virginia.",
          "answer": "House of Burgesses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native group that met the first English colonists in Virginia; the leader of this group, as with Pocahontas’ father, shares the same name.",
          "answer": "Powhatan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Englishman who was legendarily saved by Pocahontas and declared “He who will not work, shall not eat.”",
          "answer": "John Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Armed rebellion by settlers against Governor William Berkeley in 1676; it included the burning of the capital.",
          "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby Virginia city that became capital of the colony after a burning of the previous capital in 1698.",
          "answer": "Williamsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial governor who names a 1774 war and a 1775 proclamation that freed slaves who joined the British army.",
          "answer": [
            "John Murray, Lord Dunmore",
            "either",
            "both",
            "Lord Dunmore’s War",
            "Dunmore’s Proclamation"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Joseph Stalin",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Predecessor to Stalin as leader of the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Ilyich Lenin or Vladimir Ulyanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian revolutionary whom Stalin exiled and had killed in Mexico in 1940.",
          "answer": "Leon Trotsky"
        },
        {
          "question": "1945 conference, held in the Crimea, of the leaders of the US, UK, and USSR to discuss a post-World War II peace plan.",
          "answer": "Yalta Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern country where Stalin killed millions of people in a famine known as Holodomor in the 1930s.",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of centralized economic development plans developed by Stalin which continued after his death until 1991.",
          "answer": "Five-Year Plans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret police service under Stalin, responsible for carrying out executing Stalin’s mass purges; it preceded the KGB.",
          "answer": [
            "NKVD",
            "People’s Commissariat for Internal Affairs",
            "Narodnyy Komissariat Vnutrennikh Del"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaign organized by Stalin shortly before his death to arrest Jews of a certain profession, based on the false belief that they were conspiring against Soviet leadership.",
          "answer": "Doctors’ Plot"
        },
        {
          "question": "Successor to Stalin who only held his position for two years, before being replaced by Nikita Khrushchev.",
          "answer": "Georgy Malenkov"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Decline of Imperial China",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Final dynasty of China.",
          "answer": "Qing Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Century in which that dynasty fell during the Xinhai [shin-hi] Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "20th century",
            "1900s"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City where the final Emperor of China resided in the Forbidden City.",
          "answer": [
            "Beijing",
            "Peking"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellion started by the Righteous and Harmonious Fists that led to foreign domination over China.",
          "answer": [
            "Boxer Rebellion",
            "Yihetuan Movement",
            "Quan Luan Rebellion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "General and mentor to Chiang Kai-Shek who organized several post-Imperial governments.",
          "answer": [
            "Sun Yat-sen",
            "Sun Zhongsha"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Empress Dowager who led a coup against the Hundred Days’ Reform.",
          "answer": [
            "Empress Dowager Cixi",
            "Empress Xiaoqinxian",
            "Xingzhen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Last official imperial ruler of China; he was later installed by the Japanese as Emperor of Manchukuo.",
          "answer": [
            "Puyi",
            "Xuantong Emperor",
            "Kangde Emperor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Government official who assumed the name Hongxian [hong-shee-ahn] Emperor in a short-lived bid for power.",
          "answer": "Yuan Shikai"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At this battle, Charles Wikoff and three other commanders were injured or killed in under an hour, leading Ezra Ewers to assume command. The winning side at this battle came under fire from Mausers at a location called (20 pts)",
        "“Bloody Ford.” Troops from El Caney provided support for this side’s victors. Though the Buffalo Soldiers were prominent at this battle, it is more often associated with a (10 pts)",
        "cavalry unit that went on to fight at the Siege of Santiago. For ten points, name this 1898 battle in Cuba where Teddy Roosevelt fought with the Rough Riders."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of San Juan Hill",
        "Battle of San Juan Heights"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler was opposed by the Gabiniani in a conflict after this ruler turned a set of assassins over to Marcus Bibulus. In accordance with the Donations of Alexandria, this ruler became joint monarch with (20 pts)",
        "Caesarion. Plutarch relates how this ruler hid in a carpet in order to meet with Julius Caesar. This ruler allegedly (10 pts)",
        "committed suicide by allowing an asp to bite her breast after her forces were defeated at the Battle of Actium by Octavian. For ten points, name this pharaoh, the lover of Marc Antony."
      ],
      "answer": "Cleopatra VII Philopator"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work’s first section prioritizes justice over convenience by using the example of a drowning man and a plank. This work’s line “unjust law is itself a species of violence” was quoted by Mahatma Gandhi, who read it while (20 pts)",
        "in jail in South Africa. This work was itself written in jail, as its author had been arrested for refusing to (10 pts)",
        "pay taxes in protest of slavery and the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this 1849 Henry David Thoreau essay that argues for opposition to unjust government."
      ],
      "answer": "Civil Disobedience or Resistance to Civil Government"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This philosopher asked “What is the meaning of ascetic ideals?” in the third essay of a book On the Genealogy of Morality, which was a follow-up to Beyond Good and Evil. This thinker was horrified by the (20 pts)",
        "“eternal recurrence,” and he thought that the “will to power” was the driving force of life. This philosopher wrote a parable about an insane man with a lantern in (10 pts)",
        "The Gay Science. For ten points, name this German philosopher who wrote Thus Spoke Zarathustra, an important influence on Nazism who originated the phrase “God is dead.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Friedrich Nietzsche"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 17th century migration led to the rise of this industry in the town of Spitalfields. Garreurs and battandiers were types of workers in this industry that led a revolt put down by Jean-de-Dieu Soult. The (20 pts)",
        "Canut revolts occurred in this industry which was controlled by a class of financiers called fabricants. Louis XVI promoted this industry in the city of (10 pts)",
        "Lyon. James I promoted the trade of this good by planting 100,000 mulberry plants. For ten points, name this textile good that is produced by a namesake worm."
      ],
      "answer": "silk"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Candice Bergen claimed that this man gave a “perfectly intelligence speech” [sic] when he criticized the show Murphy Brown for “mocking the importance of fathers.” After comparing his length of Congressional service to a former president, this man was scolded by (20 pts)",
        "Lloyd Bentsen, who said “Senator, you’re no Jack Kennedy.” Despite that incident, this man became (10 pts)",
        "vice president after the defeat of Michael Dukakis in 1988. For ten points, name this vice president who served under George H.W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Dan Quayle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2006 in this country, police used force to bar flower vendors from a marketplace, sparking a protest in which students identified themselves by university IDs, the “I am 132” movement. A 2012 (20 pts)",
        "election in this country sparked protests when media bias allegedly contributed to the defeat of Josefina Mota, head of the PAN [spell it]. The (10 pts)",
        "PRI [spell it] currently leads, for ten points, what country where Enrique Pena Nieto was succeeded in 2018 by Andres Manuel Lopez Obrador?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man provoked the ire of his citizens when he imprisoned William de Braose’s wife after attempting to extract 40,000 marks from William. This man refused to allow Stephen Langton to become Archbishop of (20 pts)",
        "Canterbury, leading Pope Innocent III to excommunicate him. After this man was defeated by French forces at (10 pts)",
        "Bouvines [boo-veen], he was further disgraced when barons cornered him at Runnymede and forced him to give up his unlimited powers. For ten points, name this English king who, in 1215, signed the Magna Carta."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John I of England",
        "John Softsword",
        "Lackland"
      ]
    }
  ]
}